My name is Terence Tao. I'm a professor of
mathematics at the University of California,
Los Angeles. And I have a forthcoming book,
six math essentials. Today on Big Think,
I'll be talking about six essential pillars of
mathematics. How math interacts with science
historically and how it has anticipated
many of the great developments in the
sciences and how new developments in AI
will impact math and science going forward.
Thank you for watching Big Think. If you'd like
to support our work, we encourage you to join our
members community. As a member, you'll receive our
quarterly print magazine, a beautifully designed
collection of the ideas and interviews that
matter most. Big Think is for curious people
who want to take deep dives into big ideas. To
support the media you want to see in the world,
go to bigthink.com/membership.
And now back to the interview.
Chapter one, the six essential
elements of mathematics.
I decided to organize my book around six really
fundamental concepts that have origins from
thousands of years ago or centuries ago which are
um very familiar um in the early stages to to most
people but mathematicians have developed over
time to become extremely sophisticated. Numbers
is the first concept and then algebra, geometry,
probability, analysis and dynamics. These are all
very basic concepts but they've evolved into very
sophisticated mathematics. But if you strip away
all the technical complexities um they really are
just extremely intuitive concepts and the ma the
mathematics that we we we developed it's just
a precise language to describe it really really
carefully and in a way that uh that allows you to
think really clearly about these concepts. Numbers
are one of the oldest mathematical inventions and
still um the most useful really. We have records
of carvings on bones that predate the alphabet
or or other writing and it was invented multiple
times by multiple civilizations. We didn't
have numbers. Uh we would have to always speak
poetically when trying to describe any situation
and it would always be a little bit imprecise
and the next person who's communicating what what
you're saying would get it slightly different. It
allows for precision. Numbers are placeholders for
concepts like quantity and size and magnitude into
very portable things that you can communicate to
other people who may not have directly interacted
with the objects you're describing. And once
once you try to describe a very complicated
uh uh scenario with many many u moving parts, you
need um numbers and everything else that's born on
top of that. Humans are not really wired to think
in numbers. If you don't have the ability to think
quantitatively to measure both the benefits and
the costs of an action and which one is bigger,
you can make some life choices that you'll
regret later that uh uh you spend a lot of
of resources for very little gain. The first
step in being able to think more quantitatively
u for these things is is to understand numbers
and then more advanced mathematical topics like
probability and and algebra on top of that. basic
things like agriculture or or trade could not have
happened without the ability to numbers to measure
large quantities of you know grain and actually
the ability to tax uh is you you can't have a
civilization without taxation unfortunately and
that requires mathematics and numbers. Of course
not everything is is um uh is quantitative. You
know if if you want to go on a date you shouldn't
be measuring the cost and benefits of of of your
of your prospective partner. Okay. Some things
should be still be very uh subjective and and
personal but there are um increasingly in this
modern world there are lots of decisions for
example in finance or in medicine uh where some
quantitative thinking is very helpful. The thing
about numbers is that they take on a life of their
own because once you have the concept of number,
you can study numbers in um abstractly divorced
from their actual application and you find
patterns and you find um often that uh it's very
natural to extend the number system that you have
to create new numbers which you wouldn't have
thought would be applicable to your your original
context, but they fit very very well into the
number system. If you're counting sheep, you know,
sometimes you want to add sheep and you want to
subtract sheep. And so very soon you develop the
notions of addition and subtraction, but you
realize if you are only counting um counting
numbers 0 one or actually not even zero, 1 2 3 4,
you find that you can always add to these numbers
together, but you can't always subtract. If you
subtract four from three um it doesn't make any
sense. You can't take away four sheep from three
sheep. But patterns in the numbers themselves are
so regular um that uh if you just blindly apply
the rules of of of arithmetic, it feels like you
should be able to take away three from four um
and have a new number. And it it took a while,
but eventually people realize that you can invent
these negative numbers um and um and you can add
negative 1, -2,3 to your number system and zero.
And zero took a long time to to actually realize
it was a good addition to to the number system.
and you still get all the nice laws of of of
arithmetic. For example, if you take a number a
and you subtract b and then you add back b again,
you you get back a. That's one of the laws of
arithmetic and it still works even when you
have negative numbers. Similarly, uh we learned
to divide numbers by another and and we created
fractions and fractions fit very well into this
number system and then there was a shock. We
found that there were numbers uh somehow between
all these rational numbers, all these fractions,
there were numbers like the square root of two
which could not be expressed as any ratio. Um and
this was a big shock actually that they I mean
these numbers are literally called irrational
numbers which is Latin for you know insane
not unreasonable numbers but they do exist
um and they're very useful. You can never write
down all their digits or whatever in a in a on
a on a finite piece um sheet of paper. it is um
very very useful to have all these extra numbers
lying around and then eventually we uh we tried
to take square roots of negative numbers which
we couldn't do in a regular number system and we
invented complex numbers and that turned out to be
extremely useful for electromagnetics and and
quantum mechanics. It's remarkable that these
number systems which were often invented just
so that we could be better at solving equations
and and solving practical problems um end up
actually being the most natural uh language
to describe very very complicated phenomena in
the real world like quantum quantum mechanics
for instance algebra is the second layer of
abstraction over numbers. So with numbers,
we took concrete things like a bunch of sheep or
a quantity of water or whatever and we replaced
these these quantities with numbers that you can
then apply um operations to addition, subtraction,
division and so forth. Algebra is uh goes one step
further and tries to not look at specific numbers
like seven or 17. First of all, replace numbers by
even more generic placeholders. to give them names
like x and y, but to also study the operations
themselves, plus and times and and all these other
um uh operations and ask what properties do the
operations have, not just not just the numbers.
And so people discovered that the these operations
that are so useful in arithmetic themselves have
many fascinating properties. Um so addition has a
property called commutativity. If you add a to b,
that's the same as adding b to a. And that turns
out to be extremely useful property for helping
you solve problems involving addition. Similarly
for multiplication and all the other basic
arithmetic operations obey these very simple laws.
Later on we discovered that these laws also hold
for other um uh operations. For example, if I want
to take say an object and I I rotate it, I can
rotate it by 30° and then rotate by another 60°.
But if if I rotate it in the in the other order,
rotate it by 60 degrees first and 30° next, I end
up with the same position that I started with,
these two rotations are commutive. So even
though that operation has nothing to do with
um it's not really an addition or multiplication
in a traditional uh sense of numbers, it it has
the same algebraic structure. On the other hand,
some things are um do not obey the commutive law.
Like if I put on my socks and then I put on my
shoes, I get a different outcome than if I put
on my shoes first and then I put on my socks.
Those two operations do not commute. Certain
um operations u obey nice laws like uh like
the commutive law and certain operations
don't. Sometimes you you see a match the laws that
that that you you you uh you are present are very
similar to laws that we already understand for say
numbers. Um and then because of that we can take
intuition and and ideas and and and proofs and and
a theory of numbers and we can uh transfer them to
a a a different setting. For example, matrices are
a much more complicated concept than a numbers.
Not just one number, but it's a whole square array
of numbers. But it turns out that matrices obey
very similar laws of algebra to numbers. And
if you are very good at manipulating numbers,
you can start to manipulate matrices the same way.
And many of our modern technologies for example
large language models are based on being able to
manipulate matrices very very efficiently. Once
you have abstracted to get to numbers and then to
algebra then you are working with equations that
involve variables like x and y and x may have had
some physical meaning and has some specific value.
But often it can clarify your thinking to not
focus on the specific values of these numbers or
or what they represent and just manipulate these
these equations um by pure algebra just by moving
symbols around. When you first learn this it it
it feels very disconnected from your uh actual
experience but it is a very powerful technique.
One early use of algebra was the story of Johannes
Kepler who was this astronomer and scientist
who was one day walking down the streets of his
hometown and he saw um the wine market um and and
wine sellers was was selling wine by the barrel
and so some large barrels and some small barrels
uh but they were able to figure out how much wine
was in each barrel and and so that they could pay
the wine um um the wine sellers for uh for these
barrels. uh if you have a barrel and you want to
compute how much how much wine there is there. You
know, you could pour it out and into into cups
and so forth, but it was very tedious. But what
fascinated Kepler was that the person in charge
of the market had a very very efficient way to to
measure the volume of the barrel. He just had a a
stick with various markings on it and there was a
bung hole in the middle of the barrel and he just
poked the stick down the barrel into the corner
and just saw how far the stick went that he could
measure and just based on what that marking was
he could say oh this is you know 30 gallons or
whatever of wine and then they could price it.
This astounded Kepler how you could just take this
one measurement of just this one sort of diagonal
and work out the shape of the volume because some
barrels could be very tall and skinny or short and
wide and somehow this this one measurement was
somehow able to compute the volume. He did the
math. This was a puzzle to him. So he he went
home and he wrote out some equations. I assume
my barrel is maybe the radius of the barrel is r
and the height is h. You know nowadays with modern
algebra this is a question you can assign to a
high school student. This it's almost precisely
one of these word problems that that that we we
love to give our students and you can compute
the volume and you compute the um uh this length
and he found that the length did not completely
determine the the the volume but a wine seller
would want us to to sell as much wine as possible
and you know you would want to sort of maximize
how much volume you could get for a given um for a
given length. Reasoning that um you know all these
merchants were trying to maximize their profit. uh
even though he couldn't quite solve the equations
right away, if he added this profit incentive,
he did some rudimentary what we would now call
calculus. And that turned out to almost exactly
match the shape of the barrels that actually
were sold in in the marketplace. And his formulas
did actually match what what people used very
high precision. So he actually explained these
these rules which I think the the marketplace
had come up with over time just by empirical
measurement. But he had found a very satisfactory
explanation and I think this was part of the
inspiration for the the the calculus developed
by Newton and Leibniz a few centuries later.
Geometry is literally is Greek for measurement of
the earth. Since antiquity it was important to to
know you know how many miles it was to travel
from one place to another and how to navigate
uh you know in the ocean or or or out in in
in the wilderness by the stars. We needed
to understand how to use things that we could
observe like angles and distances to for very
practical problems like transportation. Just
like numbers have got various patterns like
a plus b= b plus a. Once you start measuring
distances between different points and angles,
there are lots and lots of relations between
those uh all those measurements as well. So
geometry obeys laws just like numbers obey
laws. So for example, one law is similarity.
Once you know that two shapes are similar, you
know, they have the same angles and things,
then all their sides are proportionate. Once you
know that the side of the big triangle is say two
times as big as the side of the small triangle,
then you know that all the other sides of the
big triangle are also five times as big. The
proportions are equal. The reason why this is
um so useful is that it allows you to predict the
measurement of um of distances or scales that you
couldn't directly reach, you couldn't directly
measure. You can look at a distant mountain and
you might be able to actually estimate how how
far away it is because you know something about
how tall it is and the angle of elevation is you
can use a similar triangle and you make a scale
model. So for example, now you can navigate and
you can see how to get to a distant location even
if you can't see it directly from your sailboat
or whatever. And even in ancient Greek times they
were able to measure distances to the moon and
the sun which they could not possibly measure
directly but just through the laws of geometry
which they had similar triangles and things like
that which they had already worked out at that
time they could actually get reasonably good
measurements you know without any satellites
or advanced technology. Once you know geometry
you can really extend your senses well beyond
what you can just touch and measure directly.
The fourth of math essential is probability which
is the standard way that mathematicians try to
encapsulate one of the basic features of the real
world which is uncertainty. In your primary or
high school classes when you teach mathematics
we often present very sanitized predictable word
problems. You know um you know Annie has has 30
apples. She gives half of them to uh to James. You
know how much does does James have and whatever
where everything is precise and you know all
the information. But in the real world uh there's
there is uncertainty and there's unpredictability.
So you know when you flip a coin maybe it
is heads, maybe it is tails. Now if you know
exactly how much force you apply to a coin and and
you you you knew all these um measurements, you
could maybe do enough of a simulation to actually
predict exactly uh which way the coin will land.
But this is extremely difficult um and often you
don't have that data. What was eventually realized
is that rather than try to compute exact answers
all the time for every single outcome, sometimes
you just have to accept that there's a range
of outcomes to a um to a given measurement. But
what's important is which ones are more frequent
and which ones are less frequent. And um the first
people to realize this was important were gamblers
because you know gamblers would gamble on certain
events like trying to to uh to bet that a certain
die rolls would sum up to to a certain number or
whatever. And if they could calculate the odds
correctly they could make money and if they didn't
calculate odds correctly they would lose money on
in the long run. The mathematics of probability
was was uh was created by several letters that um
some gamblers wrote to their mathematician friends
asking for help trying to to uh to optimize their
their their gambling strategies probably has has
has blossomed well beyond it it its gambling
roots. Um you know anytime we have a system
too complicated to model all the way from first
principles there's going to be some stochasticity
and we we want to have a probabilistic model.
So whether it's the stock market or whether
a drug is going to be be successful, we turn
to probability. Now quite often now sometimes
uh we don't know what the odds are. So probability
works best when it involves an event that happens
over and over again. You there are thousands and
thousands of trials and we can start getting a
good measure of the odds. If it's an event that
only happens once in a century, it may not quite
be the right uh the right mathematics and we're
still trying to work out mathematics for extremely
rare events. um that is a better replacement for
probability and there are some miracles that make
it effective. Um so you may think that every
time you do a different experiment, you know,
so instead of doing a medical trial, you're you're
trying to understand the just the outcome of of
a of a die roll or what genetic traits are going
to emerge from evolution or whatever. Um and you
would think that in every different circumstance
you get all these different distributions, you
know, so some distributions will be heavy tailed
and some will be narrow and whatever. But there
are these these funny laws in probability called
universality laws that that even very general
types of of of uh of random systems various
common shapes emerge. Um the most famous of
which is the Gaussian or what's called the bell
curve shape that many distributions like if you
take the distribution of men or heights of women
they form almost a perfect bell curve. We actually
have good explanations now. We we have understood
probability well enough that that we can explain
quite a few of these universal laws uh from
mathematics although some are still mysterious.
Analysis is how mathematics deals with two
things. One is inaccuracy in our measurements
that sometimes it's not so much randomness
but just imprecision. analysis is sort of the
mathematics of error bars where we've realized
that sometimes we we need to to understand not
only what the numerical value of various
quantities are but how much uncertainty we
have what what what are the plus and minus error
bars around them but these are concepts that you
you you can't even talk about I mean if it just
having only qualitative language of big and small
um is is is not uh it only works up to a point
we may measure say the length of an object and
it it's roughly 2 m but maybe 2 m plus or - 10 cm.
There's an approximation and there's an error and
um ideally you want the errors to be zero but
in in the real world we can't always make the
errors uh entirely zero. But sometimes uh if
we we can make the errors smaller and smaller
and if we keep making more and more precise
measurements we can make the errors shrink to
zero. But it may take an infinite amount of of of
um of precision or infinite amount of time to get
the error all the way down to zero. Analysis is
also about how we we take limits and how we deal
with infinities. In algebra, the laws of algebra
work very well when you're just taking a a finite
number of operations. If you're just taking five
things and you're adding them together, there's
there's no problem. You can you can rearrange
them in any order. But um once you start trying
to to work with an infinite number of operations,
there are some funny um paradoxes that that that
show up that that sometimes you can rearrange an
infinite number of objects and they they end up
you end up with a different sum than than before
you rearranged which doesn't happen with finite
sums. For example, if you're always betting on
say roulette or red and black, you win 50% of
the time and you lose 50% of the time. There is
a theorem um that there is no strategy that will
allow you to constantly win that will guarantee
you a win in the long run as long as you only have
a finite amount of money. No betting strategy
can beat the house basically. And so there's a
strategy of always doubling down when you lose and
just betting bigger and bigger numbers. And the
moment as long as you win at least once uh you
will get your dollar. So there was some way to
constantly beat the house. But um the problem is
that it assumes that you have an infinite amount
of money. What the strategy is doing is that it is
compressing all the risk of losing money into this
very very small event where you're always losing.
At some point you know you're you're betting
millions of dollars and at some point you become
bankrupt. So analysis helps you understand exactly
what these terror risks are and how to reason with
infinities in a way which is uh in which you avoid
all these paradoxes. Yeah, there there was a lot
of very inaccurate mathematics that was uh that
predated analysis where people were just saying,
"Oh, if I do this infinitely often, I can get rid
of of all of all these problems." And it took a
while to realize that there was a that infinity
is a very dangerous beast if you if you're not
uh trained to deal with it properly. But we we
need to deal with infinities all the time in
the real world. Well, maybe not infinities,
but we need to deal with very large numbers.
But infinity is a very good approximation for
understanding how we deal with with large
numbers. But it has to be used with care.
So one famous demonstration of of the unintuitive
nature of infinity is what's called the infinite
monkeys theorem. The u common way to to phrase
this is that if you have an infinite number of
monkeys in a room or maybe just one monkey typing
infinitely for forever uh on a typewriter and
just hitting keys at random then usually they the
monkey will just type nonsense and gibberish but
every so often the monkey will type a a word know
the or it um and sometimes it will it will type a
sentence but the infinite monkey theorem is that
if you wait long enough or you have enough monkeys
you're almost certainly guaranteed eventually
that the monkey will type whatever you like the
complete works of Shakespeare or Hamlet um
or Wikipedia or or anything. And uh you can
you can prove this mathematically that that as as
long as the probability of the monkey doing it at
least once is positive. It doesn't matter how how
small as long as it's positive if you wait long
enough eventually the probability that this this
particular pattern gets hit will eventually go to
one. It's like if you play Russian roulette
and you you you you only have one bullet in
the revolver and you keep you keep firing. Um
it doesn't matter how many chambers you have,
eventually it will eventually fire and you you
you'll get your hit for any given word or sentence
or or paragraph or whatever, your monkey will
eventually create this text, but the time taken
uh grows exponentially with with the size of
the text. So if if it's just a fourletter word,
it might just take an hour or so of typing
before the monkey gets it. But if it's already
say a sevenletter word that uh you know the word
Shakespeare for instance um then that may already
take years a sentence you know it might take
millennia and actually to get even a fraction of
Hamlet think even just a page uh would would take
way more than the age of the universe before you'd
actually see it. So infinity is actually just a
placeholder for a number anything which is which
could potentially be be far larger than any fixed
number that you could come up with. You know,
even though in the real world you don't have
infinitely many monkeys, you don't have infinite
budget. Often we we reason with infinity first in
as an idealized situation to see what is possible.
And then from there we we can we can um turn to
the more quantity questions of of exactly what can
we do with finite resources. But first you you
understand what to do with infinite resources.
When I was a kid, I used to play a lot of computer
games. For many computer games, there were certain
cheats you could you could put in your games. you
could give yourself infinite health or infinite
ammunition. And it was sometimes helpful to play
that game first with those cheats where you didn't
have to worry about managing your your health
potions or or your your ammo or whatever and
just see how to solve um how to solve the game
and then you could play it on hard on a harder
mode and then see how to to do things more more
efficiently. So many problems in math are actually
solved this way. One thing that distinguishes
math from other disciplines is that we have the
freedom to fail because failure is very cheap
in in mathematics. You know, if you're running
a business and you make a bad business decision
and your company goes bankrupt, that's a terrible
mistake. You know, if you're a surgeon and you cut
the wrong thing, that's a terrible mistake. But if
you trying to solve a math problem and you make an
incorrect assumption or something and it doesn't
work, it's not really that much of a bad mistake.
You just try again. It's it's actually a good move
when you are trying to solve a math problem is to
just first make an idealized assumption. assume
that you have, you know, um an infinite amount of
of of energy or or zero friction or or some other
unrealistic assumption. Solve the problem then and
then try to um get from the infinite world back
to the finite world. And this is where analysis
comes in to sort of carefully see what features
of of of infinite mathematics still work in
the finite world and which ones break down.
Dynamics is mathematics of change of time is the
study of how the rules of incremental change.
How a state evolves from one time to the next
all kinds of emergent and interesting behavior
which you may not expect from the uh from the
initial rules. So we have found that even very
simple rules can generate extremely complicated
emergent behavior if you iterate them long enough.
Evolution is a good example in biology. You know,
you have a bunch of organisms and they reproduce
and the fitter ones survive more often than than
the weaker ones and the organisms have certain
traits that they can pass down to descendants. And
these are very simple rules and it turns out that
you can create a a massive diversity of species
and and predator prey relationships and and and
incredibly complicated dynamics. If you're on
the freeway and and you have all these cars and
and each car is just trying to move as fast as
it can given the car in front of us, you know,
so if there's too many cars in front, you'll slow
down. If there's not many cars, you speed up. And
each individual car is not doing anything very
very complicated. It's just trying to optimize
its flow. But when you put all the cars together
and you see what it does to the whole network,
you get these amazing emergent phenomena
like traffic waves. You get these waves
that can compress and grow. Kind of like a
slinky. If you mess around with a slinky,
you can have a compression wave and an expansion
wave and it leads to phenomena which you wouldn't
initially expect like like if there is a traffic
shock like there's an accident and then the cars
pile up then even when the the traffic accident
is removed and there's no obstruction to travel
the laws of traffic if you if you iterate the
dynamics you can actually do the math and you
can see that takes a while for the compression
wave to dissipate and so living in Los Angeles
this is a a phenomena I've encountered quite
quite often that sometimes I was I encountered
a slowdown in traffic and there's no accident or
no um immediate cause was because many hours ago
there was something that caused a slowdown but
the dynamics it takes a certain amount of time
for the the the wave to dissipate. You know once
you understand the dynamics really well you can
do modeling and simulation and then you can do
things like you can you can make predictions like
if I add another lane to this uh this this freeway
will the traffic get better? Um in fact sometimes
it doesn't. that these paradoxes were actually
sometimes closing off certain lanes of traffic and
actually make the traffic the global traffic flow
uh flow faster. Now some dynamics are predictable.
Sometimes uh we have uh equilibria which are
states that just stay the same or for all time
and sometimes these equilibria are stable. If
you move a little bit away from from that state,
you you come back to that state. Like if you
have a pendulum that's going straight down,
that's a stable equilibrium. And if you modify it
a little bit, you perturb it, it will sort of move
a little bit and it'll get back towards a stable
equilibrium. But if you make a pendulum upside
down, it's balancing on the tip. It could be an
equilibrium. Like technically, it can stay in that
position forever. But any slight perturbation
will actually cause it to move away from the
equilibrium over time. So it's important to know
what equilibria are stable and which ones are not.
We are now facing a world of climate change where
we have lived for a thousand 10,000 years in the
climate in a pretty close to an equilibrium
state. Make it hotter or colder some years,
but it would bounce back to equilibrium. And we're
now actually in danger of leaving that equilibrium
and to a much less stable dynamics, which is
scary, but it needs to be modeled. Uh, and we
may need to figure out how to adapt and change
our agriculture and all our other practices.
Understanding dynamics and which systems are
stable, which ones are not, which ones are
chaotic, which ones are predictable. It's actually
extremely important. There are very mundane things
like predicting the weather. You know, we take
for granted that that we have accurate weather
predictions for the next seven days. This was this
is actually an amazing achievement of atmospheric
scientists. They they collected lots and lots
of data, but they also solved a lot of dynamical
systems problems that allowed over the years got
the error rate down to a point where we we can
actually reliably predict weather. forecasted to
say a week in advance. It's still not completely
100% accurate, but it's much more accurate than
just guessing. Systems which involve a lot of
a lot of humans are still very unpredictable. So
the dynamics of the stock market um or or politics
this this this is well beyond ability of current
um uh dynamical systems theory to to model but
but natural systems and some human systems like
traffic uh we can actually model. So it it is a
fairly advanced area of mathematics. We often need
a lot of computer simulations and we need to solve
uh very advanced differential equations but it
can give some very valuable insights. One of the
discoveries of dynamical systems is is that most
systems exhibit what's called chaos. And this was
this came as a surprise in the 17th century. So
Newton when he introduced this law of gravitation.
Uh one of the great successes of this theory
was that it explained the motion of the moon
around the earth and the earth around the sun he
could explain retroactively um all these funny
laws of Kepler like why planets move in ellipses
and things like that. And so he solved what we
now call the two body problem that if you have two
massive objects like the sun and the earth and you
move them around and you govern by a single law
of motion Newton's law of inverse square law of
universal gravitation he could solve the equations
using his newly derived theory of calculus and he
could have perfect formulas for for the orbits
and they were perfect ellipses exactly verifying
Kepler's theory it was an amazing achievement once
he solved the two-body problem it was it was very
natural and many of Newton's successor And I think
also Newton himself tried to solve the three-body
problem. I think Newton once said that this was
the only problem that ever gave him a headache
because no matter what he tried, he could not
get an exact solution. Um leading societies of
the time offered major prizes for anyone who could
who could write the solution. This was considered
one of the major open problems in mathematics.
We still do not have an exact solution for these
equations. And the belief now is that there isn't
really one that you can write down as a nice neat
formula. But when you actually look at the numeric
you see that it is not some nice periodic pattern.
It often stays periodic for a long period of time
but then suddenly it will change to something a
little bit different and then it will change yet
again. We suspect now that our solar system which
currently has what eight planets or something
that in the past there were other planets that
were in the system and they mostly moved in sort
of elliptical orbits like as as according Kepler.
Every so often the um the little interactions
between the gravitational force of Jupiter,
exert or Mars and so forth would jiggle these
um these planets a little bit out of their usual
orbit and occasionally they would just veer off
completely and sometimes two two planets would
collide or one would escape the solar system
and you know for example there's an asteroid
belt which we believe is it's a remnant of a
collision from millions of years ago. Even the
most stable of systems like the solar system that
looks like it hasn't changed for millennia, there
are long-term instabilities in in that system.
Once you move beyond the simplest of systems there
um there's lots of little tiny um unpredictable
or or very hard to predict deviations that that
that occasionally can can pile up just like
occasionally a bunch of monkeys can sort of
write the works of Shakespeare. Occasionally um
gravitational perturbations can can set an entire
planet off uh uh off course. So often actually
uh in the most advanced forms of dynamics today,
even if you start off with with a completely
deterministic system with no unpredictability
whatsoever, we find that the best way to
model it actually is to to approximate it by a
um using probability and just assume that there's
going to be some random fluctuations back and
forth and eventually the your predictions
will just get blurrier and blurrier which
which just seems to be a fundamental
feature of chaos which many systems have.
So these six essentials um they don't describe all
the mathematics but they do describe six of the
great themes that mathematics tries to encapsulate
and there's there's much more precise. This is
just a taste of of what what goes on these days.
Chapter 2 how math solves the problems of science.
I view STEM as a whole ecosystem. At the bottom
there's basic research um like mathematics and
some other fundamental sciences where we pursue
things mostly driven by curiosity. We see a
phenomenon that is crying out for an explanation
or further study. It may not be a phenomenon
that we urgently need to solve right now for an
immediate problem but it's something that looks
like it should have an interesting answer.
And so mathematics is is is almost entirely
curiosity driven like that. There's some pattern
in numbers. there's some pattern in shapes. People
just observed while trying to do something else
and we want to understand it better. At some point
uh other scientists are able to connect that
pattern to something that they're studying and
and some mathematical numerical pattern might show
up in the behavior of of of insects um in a swarm
or in a stock market or whatever. Um and then
um sometimes once you understand it you you can
actually convert it into some useful technology
or you can have a company that actually makes some
money out of out of somehow some service related
to to that uh exploiting that phenomenon. We often
don't uh we don't see that. I mean that that's
that that's much further down the pipeline. What
you do need is that you do need the people doing
the basic sciences to talk to the people doing
applied sciences and they have to talk to people
who are doing engineering and they have to talk
to people in industry. If you didn't have one
of these communities, then you wouldn't have
this pipeline of getting from curiosity driven
questions to actual, you know, commercial results,
you know, you know, like um like the ability to
communicate across the across the planet with
almost zero cost. This is part of what Eugene
Wigner calls the unreasonable effectiveness of
mathematics in the physical sciences. He observed
that mathematicians often discover concepts such
as complex numbers or curved space or whatever
just because it it seems to be a natural extension
of um the mathematical objects they're already
studying. Uh and then 10 20 50 years later some
scientists discover that that these concepts
that introduced for fun or for play were in
fact exactly what was or almost exactly what was
needed to understand some new new type of science.
So that's a really amazing phenomenon and we still
don't have a good explanation really for for why
uh that actually works. So one historical
example of how curiosity driven mathematics
led to a really deep uh scientific advance uh
was the story of the parallel postulate Euclid
in like the 3rd century BC introduced the notion
of proof of being able to explain complicated
results in geometry in this case from simpler
axioms. for example that the sum of angles of
a triangle always added up to 180° He was able to
explain that in terms of simpler axioms. He laid
out five axioms of geometry that he thought he
reduced all the other facts he knew about points
and angles and lines to these five statements and
four of them were very straightforward like if I
give you two points there's always a line you can
draw between them right things like that. These
are very straightforward non-controversial axioms.
But there was this one axiom which is called the
parallel postulate which gave him a lot of grief
and in fact his original version was very very
complicated. Um it got simplified but even even
the simplified version always was controversial.
The simplified version is that if you have
a line and you have a point and the point is
not on the line then there's exactly one line you
can draw through that point which is parallel to
the first line. By parallel I mean that it never
crosses this first line. So that was this axiom
that you can always draw a parallel line through
any other point and there's only one. You cannot
draw two parallel lines. Once you have that you
can do all kinds of things. You can derive what
I just said the angles of a triangle at 180°
and all the other classic results of Euclidean
geometry. But it was a very ugly axiom compared
to the other four which were which are really
elegant. Eventually they realized that that what
they had done was that they there actually were
multiple geometries beyond Euclidean geometry.
There's something called spherical geometry
where there's no parallel lines at all. Um so in
spherical geometry instead of lines you have great
circles like the equator or a longitude and
these great circles on the sphere they always
intersect. You can never make two parallel great
circles. So there are no parallel lines and then
there's this weirder geometry which is harder to
visualize called hyperbolic geometry where lines
actually diverge from each other and have lines
that start off looking parallel but they they
move further and further apart and and in fact
now there are actually multiple parallel lines
you can draw from one point to a given line. And
those two geometries are entirely self-consistent.
And eventually it was just accepted that there
was there were more geometries out there than
just Euclidean geometry. So these were the first
two non-Euclidean geometries to be discovered.
Spherical geometry and hyperbolic geometry. But
once we had sort of freed of our notion that
there's only one geometry, this opened all the
floodgates and people studied all kinds of other
geometries. So all kinds of curved spaces, you
know, spaces that were shaped like donuts or had
twists in them. There are geometries where um you
know if you're right-handed you can go off explore
the universe and come back and if you start off
right-handed you will come back left-handed. Um
that there there are geometries where where you
can change your orientation just by by by travel.
So which is very unintuitive or you can
come back smaller or larger than than than
what you started with. People developed
all these geometries and they developed
um a very nice language for for describing all um
all these geometries. uh it's called Riemannian
geometry after Bernard Riemann and but it was a
curiosity I mean there were these abstract curved
spaces but you know the the universe we lived in
seemed completely flat but then Einstein when he
was trying to understand gravity he eventually
came to conclusion that what gravity was doing
was it was bending space and time in a certain
way and he needed a language to to describe how
space and time could bend in such a way that
light rays would would become not straight and
sometimes times you know they would hit each other
or or diverge. He asked his mathematician friend
if there was any existing mathematics that would
describe this and he he said oh yeah there's this
bright chap Bernard Riemann who developed this
theory but it turned out to be almost exactly the
right language to describe the Einstein equations
there's a notion of curvature that some space can
have positive curvature negative curvature in
Riemannian geometry and the Einstein equations
turned out extremely simple in to state in this
language that basically mass and energy create
curvature that the curvature of space and time
is proportional to how how much mass and energy
you have in your system. And that's basically
the Einstein equations. Now, solving them is a
different matter. They're extremely hard to
model. Even the question of for how to model
two colliding black holes, we can barely do it
with modern supercomputers. But but stating the
the the equations is actually extremely natural
once we had this language. Another example of
um of how mathematical curiosity led to like
really practical developments centuries later
is the story of sphere packing. There was uh some
uh British sailor um who was just curious about
the question of you know there's a certain
number of cannonballs they had to stack in
the hold of of their ship and these are these are
round cannonballs they're not they're not square
so when you when you stack them there's a certain
amount of wasted space and he was curious what is
the most efficient way to pack cannonballs so you
can get the most cannonballs into a certain amount
of space and so he asked a physician friend who
happened to be Johannes Kepler eventually proposed
that the most efficient packing should be the
same packing that that you see in nowadays in
supermarkets when you pack oranges. It's what's
called a hexagonal close packing. You pack layer
by layer. Each layer is sort of the triangular
grid of cannonballs or oranges and then you
stack another triangular grid on top of it just
shifted by a little bit and then you stack it back
and there's a a regular pattern which is the most
natural pattern and it's about 76% efficient. And
Kepler thought this was the um the best you could
do that. there was no clever way to to to squeeze
in any any any more space but he couldn't actually
prove it. So this became known as the Kepler
conjecture. Um and it was one of the most famous
unsolved problems in geometry for for centuries in
two dimensions. Uh I think it was solved by about
1900 or something like you're packing discs in a
plane. That's a simpler problem. That one there's
a similar lattice of triangular lattice and and
that was relatively easy to prove that this was
the optimal one. three dimensions are just too
many possibilities. There was no way there. Um,
in fact, we still do not have a nice simple proof
of the Kepler conjecture that that that humans
can completely understand by themselves. The
conjecture was eventually solved. It eventually
got published I think in 1998, but it required
uh computers. It was one of the first computer
assisted proofs. There was a team of referees
who I think uh said that they could not verify
all of the computations but they at least believe
that the the strategy is correct but there were
still lingering doubts. It is only much more
recently 2014 I think and finally um the proof was
converted to what is called a a proof assistant
language computer language that is specifically
designed to check proofs with 100% certainty. So
the Kepler conjecture is now formally verified. we
are now 100% certain it is true but mathematicians
were not content with just that the three
dimensional problem so they also asked what
happens if you're in four dimensions or five
dimensions or six dimensions so here of course
there is no practical you know I mean there are
no four dimensional oranges or or cannonballs that
you would like to like to pack but people still
ask this question people also ask what happened
if instead of a continuous space um you have a
discrete space in particular computer scientists
once computer computer science became developed
We realized that in addition to the geometry of
regular space where XYZ where coordinates are
given by real numbers, we're interested in
studying the geometry of of strings of bits. So
this is now very um divorced sounding from the
original sphere packing problem both because now
you have many many dimensions like like thousands
and thousands of dimensions and space is now
discreet rather than continuous but still it
is geometry and and many of the techniques
to understand sphere packing still work.
uh when you when you're in a setting. And then it
turned out that this setting of this problem of of
packing spheres as efficiently as possible into um
on this big huge cube of of bit strings it turns
out to be extremely practical. When cell phones
became digital, they um every signal that you
that you send, you know, like an image or a text
or whatever is encoded as some bitstring which is
then sent over um over um some wireless network.
But there are other people also sending you the
signals and you don't want your signal to be
corrupted by interference and be mistaken for for
someone else's signal. So you want to keep each
different signal that that comes out. You want to
keep them as as separated from each other in this
space of of bitstrings as possible. And it turns
out mathematically this problem of separating all
these signals so that there's no way that one can
be confused for another is almost exactly the
sphere packing problem except that it's in high
dimensions and it's discreet. All the mathematics,
well, not all of it, but a lot of the mathematics
that was used to understand sphere packings
could be used to design uh really efficient
sphere packing codes and not just to design codes,
but also to to to tell engineers what was the what
is the theoretical limit of communication like
what what is the maximum number of of bits per
second you could possibly hope to um to send in
a certain wireless spectrum. So that gave really
good um benchmarks to measure how efficient
your your protocol was. They you could price
how many billions of dollars you should pay for
a certain spectrum wireless spectrum because now
you know exactly how much uh data you can push
through that. And so like the entire wireless
telecommunication industry um is is based on
being able to to to pack oranges in really high
dimensions. One of the applications of mathematics
that I was involved in that I'm most proud of is
the story of compressed sensing. So I was once at
an interdisciplinary program at a math institute
here in Los Angeles um and I met with a friend of
mine who is a statistician and he was working with
an electrical engineer and trying to improve um
imaging medical imaging um and specifically MRI
scans at the time uh MRI scans were were quite
slow. uh you had to sit in this scanning machine
for like 3 minutes so that you could collect
enough data from all different angles that the the
scan could reconstruct a good image of your body
and be able to pick up tumors or cysts or anything
else which is sort of medically important uh to
uh to um to resolve. But if you only sat in the
machine for a short period of time like say half
a minute you will not get enough data. Um so if
you tried the standard reconstruction algorithm
from all the data to recover the image uh using
what's called least squares approximation which
is the standard technique at the time you would
get an image that was so blurry and so res so so
low resolution that you could not tell anything
useful for diagnosis purposes. So we had to sit
in these machines for for minutes and minutes
and if you were a kid sometimes they you had to
be sedated because the kid would wriggle around
and not follow instructions after like the second
minute. So they were trying a new technique not
least squares uh something called total variation
minimization. They had a hunch that that this
other method might perform a little bit better
but so they they tried it on some test data. They
were expecting a slightly sharper image than the
least squares approximation but they got perfect
resolution that they got back almost exactly the
correct image even though they only took a few
measurements. It would be like giving someone a
crossword puzzle where you had only filled in,
you know, 10% of of of of the letters and
suddenly they could fill in all the other
letters without having to look up the clues. They
couldn't explain this and and they showed this to
me and my first instinct was you made a mistake.
You could not possibly have done what you said
you did. And in fact, I'm going to prove to you
that that there was not enough information in
the data that you you took to make to make this
uh measurement possible. So I I I went home that
night. I tried to write down a proof that that
there was no way to just correctly guess the the
right image from the small amount of data that
they were measuring. And while writing it down,
I found one of my steps does not work. And in
fact, in fact, it showed the opposite that if a
certain measurement matrix had a certain property,
then actually what they were doing was actually
going to work. And then I checked that what that
their measurement matrix actually did seem to obey
this property. So I actually understood uh how um
how the method worked and so I went back to them
the next day and explained this and they got very
excited and we wrote a couple papers and that got
everyone else excited. This method that they had
stumbled upon was not completely new. There were
seismologists who had discovered a similar method.
So they had a se a different problem where they
were trying to understand the fault lines to
locate the fault lines of a crust based on on
a small amount of of seismic data. And astronomers
had a similar problem that they were trying to to
measure the location of stars or something using
a very small amount of of observed data. And there
are a couple other disciplines where a similar
problem of trying to extract a high quality
image from a very small amount of signal had had
occurred. each case they had found some ad hoc fix
that could kind of squeeze more data out of um a
more uh better resolution out of the data they had
but they could not explain mathematically
why it worked. The seismologist thought,
"Oh, here's a trick, but it only works for
seismographs." And the astronomers had a trick,
but it only worked for astronomy. But once we
found the mathematical explanation, we found
that this was a general technique that we we now
call compressed sensing. And it's useful for MRI,
but it's also useful for wireless broadband. It's
useful for for certain types of sensor networks.
Once we figured out the underlying mathematics,
we could see all the other applications that
it's useful for. And so now compressed sensing is
taught in textbooks right next to least squares.
So sometimes at least squares it's the right
thing to do and sometimes compressed sensing
is the right thing to do. Sometimes neither.
It's now a a very very well developed theory.
I was quite pleased to be involved at the very
beginning of that. It's a fascinating interplay
between mathematics and science. So we have this
unreasonable effectiveness of of mathematics where
mathematical discoveries are often end up being
the the best way to explain physical phenomena.
Philosophers and historians have have debated
why this is the case. Um, one of my theories is
that whenever we learn anything uh whether it's
math or science or any other subject, the first
theories or explanations that we um we make are
often um not the best. We don't understand what
is the cleanest way to to to express something.
And before you understand something completely,
you might have an overly elaborate explanation for
why something is true. But often the the the true
explanation is is is more elegant and shorter and
simpler than our initial attempts to describe the
um the phenomenon. But finding the the short
explanation takes time because you have to sort of
unlearn certain um assumptions that you might have
that turn out to be to be incorrect. For example,
with with Einstein's theory of relativity,
one of the key assumptions that people had
before Einstein was was that was that time was
universal. everyone had the same notion of time.
You know that that an hour for me is the same as
an hour for you. That mindset uh really blocks you
from from from finding the right way to explain
gravity in particular. But once you accept that
everyone has their own relative notion of time um
then you can find the right language to explain
things properly. Mathematicians also try to take
phenomena that they first understand using very
inefficient language and try to condense it.
try to find the the the most concise elegant
explanation of a mathematical phenomenon. And I
think just because there's only so many ways you
can you can say things concisely. It just happens
that um that uh that often the concise way to
describe some mathematical phenomenon is also a
concise way to describe a physical phenomenon.
So that is that is my theory. Unfortunately, we
only have one timeline of science. If you only
have one history of scientific development and
we have maybe a 100 turning points in science
and that's a little bit of data and you can make
some theories. I would love in the future in the
far future maybe we will meet other civilizations
and we will see their history of science and we
will see whether they also had ke their version
of Kepler and Einstein and Newton and whether it
um what they they followed a similar track or
a completely different track I don't know the
funny thing about doing mathematics is that so you
know there's this stereotype that you know we're
all geniuses and you know we're stuck at a problem
and then you get this eureka insight, a light bulb
goes on and um and like you get this genius idea
out of nowhere. I would love for that to happen to
me actually. This this does not happen um so often
to me. What what does happen when I do work on a
problem is that I try something and it doesn't
work. Okay, I try something else and it kind of
works but it gets stuck at a certain point. Um but
now at least I know kind of there's at least one
obstacle and I need to find some tool that is will
will help me deal with that obstacle. And so maybe
um I will now identify a sub problem which has
the same type of difficulty but is simpler and I
try to solve that one first. Uh and if I can do
that one then I can try to scale up back to the
original problem and I go back and forth. Often
a lot of what you're doing is that you are you
are exploring the negative space of the problem
like all the the techniques that don't work and
um eventually if you have enough of the negative
space the the path forward becomes clear almost
by elimination that there's only sort of one
thing to do that could work. Um, some sometimes
there's nothing that can work and then you give
up on the problem. But there's this repeated what
you might call failure, but it really is kind of
just just really understanding the limitations
of what different approaches can do. And then
after weeks or months, you know, of of this,
the answer becomes clear. But by that point,
it's so internalized what the difficulties
are that it doesn't feel amazing to you anymore.
It feels natural. Like, of course, you had to do
this because there's this difficulty. you must go
around this this pothole. You must do this step
first because you know in five lines you're going
to need this hypothesis to to solve this problem.
You you just become so um attuned to the
problem that everything becomes natural.
Um yeah or sometimes you never solve the problem
because you never attune and and you and you give
up. The the feeling I get is never so much eureka
but it's always oh how come I missed this early?
I was so stupid. Um but often it it's it's the
constant experimentation and and and failure that
really primes you to find uh to accept the right
solution. There's this dramatic contrast between
the standards we assign to outcomes and the
standards we assign to process. So for outcomes,
mathematics very famously has a very high
standard of correctness. You know, for a
given problem, there's a correct answer and lots
of incorrect answers. And and when we grade our
um students homework in mathematics, you
know, if you didn't if you get your sign
wrong or whatever and you got the wrong answer,
you got all these all these negative marks,
you get criticized if you make math mistakes in
your final answer. One consequence of that is that
many students who go through, you know, say a high
school level of mathematics become very averse to
making any mistakes whatsoever in um when they
try to approach a math problem. Paradoxically,
um the process of arriving at the answer is is
almost the complete opposite where you almost
have to make mistakes over and over again and you
have to try the stupid things first to appreciate
why the clever things work. There's a quote by
Niels Bohr who's a physicist who said that an
expert is someone who has made all the mistakes
that can be made in a very narrow field. You
don't publish these mistakes. you execute these
mistakes in your process in order to locate the
correct answer but only after exploring a lot of
incorrect answers first. It's it's very important
I think to to normalize uh failure in the process
to disclose that behind every successful solution
to a problem there are dozens of of of incorrect
attempts and it's not because the people trying
these problems were were stupid but this is
often just part of of the learning process.
Chapter 3. How AI is changing
math and science forever.
Science and mathematics has uh changed a lot over
the centuries. Traditionally in science uh the two
major paradigms were theory and experiment.
um like you would you would create a theory
like you know Kepler might create a theory of how
planets move or or Newton might create a theory of
gravity and then there's this experimental um
data that you would run an experiment and and
see what happens and then you try to see if the
theory and the experiment fit. Math was a little
different in that it was almost entirely theory.
Um there's there are very very few experiments
that you would do purely in mathematics. There
were a few for example Gauss famously computed
the first 100,000 prime numbers and that was
a data set that he used to make predictions.
he predicted what we now call the prime number
theorem. But science and experiment were the two
major forms of science. Then later on simulation
came along um that you didn't have to run a a
big expensive experiment. Sometimes you could
just simulate uh let's say um a hurricane in
in a supercomputer instead of in real life. And
then later on big data came along that um rather
than than just do a small number of experiments
to try to confirm or deny um a specific theory,
you could take megabytes or petabytes of data and
try to discern patterns, try to extract out laws
from just massive data sets. Um and that's a more
emerging type of science. But now all these modes
of science are being transformed because we now
also have AI to to to help us. So so in the past
every one of these ways of doing science had
to be done by human scientists. You know you
had to have someone to perform the experiments or
someone to do the theoretical calculations or run
the simulations um or go through the data and you
could use computers for some of that but you have
to but even then you have to program the um the
data analysis tool or whatever and you still need
a lot of expertise. You know, we have automated
labs that can that can perform experiments
automatically. Um, you can you can get a coding
agent to run a simulation for you and you can try
to to also run automated data analysis. Um, and
increasingly you can also do automated theory. You
can take some mathematical problem and ask what
are the consequences of these hypotheses and these
axioms. What what conclusion should you get? These
tools can now be done at scale um much faster.
He could potentially run many more theoretical
analyses than than any one human scientist could.
On the other hand, this is not the only thing that
we want. There's value in doing things a slow way,
you know. So, a scientist who spending hours
and hours working things out on pen and paper
uh doing the experiments in the field with
with their bare hands and actually debugging
the simulations that show up, they often learn
a lot of of extra insight beyond just getting
the answer that they're trying to seek. They can
find they can discover new phenomena. They can
see connections. They can see similarities to some
some previous thing that's been studied elsewhere
in the literature and they can communicate
what what they uh what they are finding to
other people. So there is this paradox that on
the one hand AI are becoming more powerful and
more capable um and and making fewer mistakes and
they are ostensibly achieving a lot of the goals
that we want we think scientists are trying to to
do. They're they're running experiments. They're
analyzing data. They're writing papers. But it
may be that it comes at the cost of the AI becomes
picks up some skill, but but no human scientist
gets any better at doing the science. No human can
communicate exactly what just happened and and and
why this this scientific discovery is interesting,
why this proof is new and and and what features
it has and how it connects. We may have to sort of
redesign our um conception of what science is and
what we actually want out of science. What exactly
is science for? And and what are we trying to do?
And is there a danger that we are optimizing the
wrong thing when we are pointing our AI tools at
science? One analogy I've given in the past is
that science is a little bit like going on a hike.
You've heard there's some interesting waterfall,
some beautiful waterfall out there. So you decide
to to to to go hike with some friends to to
uh to find it, but you need to make a map. you got
lost. You get lost a little bit, but maybe while
getting lost, you discover something else which
is interesting and you make a note of it. Um,
on the way to to this waterfall, you find an even
more spectacular waterfall in the distance. You
can't get there yet, but maybe some future hiker
will figure out a way to get there, too. And so,
there's there's a whole process to get to
your goal, which um is also very valuable.
But these tools, these AI tools, they can be
like helicopters that will just fly you directly
to this waterfall and you can see it and then
you fly back, but you learn nothing about how
to get there. You you you may not see any other
interesting phenomena than the specific thing that
you asked for. And so even though technically
you achieve your goal much more efficiently,
there may be something that that is lost. Modern
AIs are powered by a a type of algorithm known
as machine learning, which is trying to predict
patterns in data. So a very simple example of
machine learning is regression. So if you have
some inputs and you some outputs like let's say
you observe that if you feed um some animal more
food they get they get bigger right? So you can
plot how much food you give various animals
and and you plot their weight or something
and you get some dots on on a graph and if you're
lucky they will they will fit some line and then
um and that line becomes your prediction. So then
if you give this dogs this sort this much food you
they would gain this much weight. Now in the real
world um you don't always get these nice linear
relationships. Often there are many many inputs
and there's many many outputs and the relationship
can be can be really complicated. But sometimes
the data has a shape and and um there we now have
all kinds of clever ways to kind of detect this
shape and try to fit curves to to these input
output pairs. What uh large language models which
power chat bots and things like that they're just
playing the game of naming the next word in
a sentence. Roughly speaking, if I say roses
are red, violets are blank. What is the next word
to fill the sentence? You can probably guess the
answer is blue. That's an output. You can imagine
this giant plot where the inputs are all these
incomplete sentences and the outputs are the words
you want to complete and you got all these dots in
this high dimensional space and you want to fit
some curve to it that will um try to explain what
is the most likely word to come out. Sometimes
there's more than one answer. Hello, my name is
you know there could be many many names you could
put after the end of the sentence. So you don't
always get a single answer but you could try to
get the most plausible answer. People have tried
this and and you know the the autocomplete feature
on your phone does this you know like you you text
something and it will suggest the next word and
sometimes it's kind of right sometimes it's silly.
Once you have any kind of operation like this it
creates some dynamics and you can just keep you
know many people have just played on their phone
just press autocomplete over and over again and
but you get these these gibberish sentences. Okay.
Um you get monkeys typing on typewriters. But the
uh the magic of LLMs is that if you um train
these LLMs on enough data, okay, so trillions and
trillions of data points and you you um you really
try to fit as good a curve as possible and this
takes like millions and millions of dollars of of
computing power and months and months of of time.
Then suddenly uh even when you iterate, it stays
coherent. it begins to sound not like monkeys,
but it actually sounds like a human speaking. And
somehow we don't fully understand why that's the
case. But what seems to be true is that language
like like English or other natural languages
contains a lot of hidden patterns that we're
not consciously aware of. I mean, we know some
of the laws of English, you know, there's laws
of grammar and things, but there are there are
sort of unspoken unwritten rules of of language
that humans pick up. you know, a a human child,
even though they're not taught, you know, what a
noun is, what a verb is or whatever, they can they
can pick up what order uh English words go in,
just by continual exposure to the language, it
seems like you can teach these models to also pick
up patterns in language to the point where you can
give them math questions. The answer to 2 plus 3
is, and they will they will say five. They have
been trained to to get the the correct answer to
to at least simple math questions. Once you have
a little bit of ability to to speak English, you
can kind of go in loops and and sort of check your
work and make fewer mistakes and you can prompt
these models to to to proceed step by step and
and and not say something unless it's been double
checked and so forth. And so they become a little
bit smarter, quote unquote, to the point where
they can solve many, many complicated tasks, but
they're still just guessing the next word to say.
It's not really grounded in any deep understanding
of the real world. It's just that they they just
have seen the patterns in in the English language
or other language that they've absorbed so well
that they can mimic people who are speaking uh in
intelligent fashion and they can present as being
intelligent long enough that they can fool us but
long enough they can actually do useful things. So
you know we can now solve certain math problems by
asking the LLM to provide a proof and sometimes
the proof is complete rubbish but if you loop
it enough and you have enough checks um you can
actually uh start having a positive success rate.
Um so it's it's a very strange way of solving
problems like it is it is completely orthogonal
to the way we normally think of intelligence as
being very grounded methodical thinking first
principles. You know, it's like having someone
who knows a lot and is but is slightly drunk
and is sort of throwing out ideas, but with enough
guidance, uh, you you can actually extract useful
output. It's not the most advanced mathematics out
there actually. Um, but you give it a lot of data
and a lot of time and a lot of other band-aids
and things and it actually works pretty well. I
find that some of the debate on AI's uh role in in
science and other disciplines is we often default
to a one dimensional view of thinking like this.
there's there's easy tasks and and and hard tasks
and very hard tasks and and and humans are can can
do tasks up to a certain level and AIs can do task
to a certain level and so which one is which one
is better right that's kind of a one dimensional
way of thinking but what I found uh when when sort
of working with AIs and and comparing their way of
solving problems to humans way of solving problems
is that they are really quite complementary human
experts um uh will will focus on depth you know
so like a human mathematician which will solve
thousands and thousands of problems they can work
on but they will pick one or two problems that
they think are are difficult but not so difficult
that they're impossible but they're difficult
enough that the the exercise of trying to make
a bit of progress towards them will reveal all
kinds of insights that they can share and maybe
their students or some other collaborators or or
other people can build upon what they do when
we point the AIs at really difficult problems
where none of the standard techniques apply they
are still very very bad at I mean they're just
randomly guessing but they excel at breadth. So
if you if you point them at a thousand problems
um of various difficulties now some may be just
too hard but there will be some which actually
are within reach of existing methods and there's
some method out there in the literature which will
solve your problem or maybe you have to combine
together two separate methods and it's just that
there there's just not enough human experts
to look at all these problems and the human
experts that do look at these problems they
may not realize that there was this obscure
paper from a journal um in 1970 that actually
has the key idea that will solve this problem.
They don't have the patience or the time to sort
of go through all the different combinations of
how which technique might work on which problem.
But the AIs, you know, they will somewhat randomly
they will take sort of educated guesses as to what
techniques might work for a problem and some of
them will be stupid and but some of them might
work and through all these combinations we're
finding that sometimes they can catch they can
catch a solution that that the rest of all the
humans have missed. Occasionally the consensus
the conventional wisdom on of of the experts
is wrong. You know that we all think that that a
problem has a positive answer but actually the has
a negative answer and we just didn't look at the
negative case too much because we thought everyone
thought that the the answer was true but an AI may
not have that preconception. So uh sometimes the
AI just serves as an independent pair of eyes.
And so some problems that we thought were very
difficult had a surprisingly simple solution which
in retrospect we should have as maybe we should
have gotten ourselves too. They're beginning
to become successful at when you point them
at a very broad range of problems and they solve
some percentage of them. Like maybe you point them
at a thousand problems and they solve 5% of those
problems. That's still 50 problems solved. you can
already have tools that in some sense outperform
humans mathematicians by raw number of problems
solved. Um now the 50 problems that get solved may
not be the 50 problems that you most want solved.
They could be 50 random problems. Um but still it
it is it is very impressive. What I think we will
have to do as a profession is find ways to um to
incorporate this new capability to to solve some
problems at broad scales um and somehow figure
out how to to to make that mesh with our existing
capability to solve a few deep problems very
slowly. Kepler's story of how he found his famous
laws of motion is a is a fascinating one. It shows
how important the process is. Kepler learned of
Copernicus' theory of the motion of the planets.
And Copernicus had roughly worked out how far the
Earth was from the Sun, how far Mars was and so
forth. And Kepler noticed that the ratios of these
um orbits looked a little bit like the like
certain ratios that showed him in geometry. And so
eventually he proposed that actually if you take
spheres one sphere for every planet and he had six
planets known at the time that he could inscribe
five platonic solids you like a dodecahedron and
a cube and a tetrahedron and so forth between
these six spheres and he thought it would get
a perfect fit and this explained the shape of the
solar system in terms of the five platonic solids.
This was his beautiful geometric idea. It was only
after he managed to get his hands on some really
high quality um observational data of Tycho Brahe
which he had to fight for actually and possibly
even steal and he tried to fit it his theory
to this this data and he found that it didn't
actually quite fit that with the precision that
Tycho's data um offered he could not quite get
these spheres to fit and in fact he discovered
from that process that the the orbit of Mars
and Earth could not be circles at all that there
had to be some other shape. He spent many years
um figuring out what to do. I think I I don't know
how long he held on to this this theory of of the
platonic solids and you can see in his writings
he tried many other things. He tried to to make
the circles off center and at some point he landed
on the ellipse and then suddenly everything fit.
It does show that there is an interplay between
theory and experiment. You know that that you
can pose a theory if it doesn't fit the data it's
it it may not be a good theory. But um it's it's
more complicated than that too. Before Kepler,
one of the criticisms of Copernicus's theory was
that already Copernicus acknowledged that that his
measurements were worse than the best predictions
available at the time. So the best models were
the geocentric models which had been developed
by the Greeks and then by the Arabs and Indians.
There were many many adjustments and fine-tuning
and they had a very very precise model that could
predict in a very complicated way where all the
planets would be. uh and Kepler Copernicus's model
was worse. Just knowing agreement of data is not
necessarily um the the only metric. It was only
after Kepler found his his revised model where
the orbits were not circles but ellipses that the
heliocentric model became more accurate than the
geocentric model. What this tells you is that is
that science is um you can't always get instant
feedback as to whether you've solved a scientific
problem or not. If Kepler and and Copernicus had
AIs and they asked them to predict a model for for
for the universe, it could be that the AIs that
generated the correct heliocentric model would
be discarded because initially their predictions
were not as good as as as the geocentric ones. It
takes time to really digest all these theories and
see how they fit with everything else that we
know about planets and motion and gravity and
everything. One concern actually is that AI are
too fast. there's a danger that these AIs will
do what's called overfitting and and create
a very complicated model which is not which
has nothing to do with what's actually going on
but just fits your data extremely extremely well
um but it doesn't extrapolate beyond that that
that data set how we incorporate AI into the
scientific discovery process will be a challenge
it can certainly accelerate individual steps of of
the process you know you can make experimentation
faster um you can you can write code faster you
can write your papers faster but science as a
whole may not necessarily accelerate just because
every single component gets faster. There's a
danger that that we will optimize uh the wrong
thing when we when we point AI at science and
we will on paper get all these amazing successes
and but find out that science is not actually
advancing as it in the way that it used to. But
we will find out it's still better to have these
tools than not have them. But we're still learning
how to use them most efficiently. Part of what
we do is is we solve problems and and we we try
to find solutions to problems and and and prove
things. Uh and proofs go through a certain life
cycle. First of all, you have to to to generate
a proof for solution. And this used to be quite
hard, but but some of the proofs that you generate
are incorrect. Um so then you have to to verify
them, check which one check that is correct. Uh
and that also used to be quite tedious. But both
of these of these tasks are becoming more and more
automated. So we we beginning to see more and more
proposed solutions to various problems and many
of them are actually correct but proofs are also
getting longer. Uh and when when when they're
written by AIs they are often not very pleasant
to read. An AI generated proof might might spend
a lot of time talking about something very trivial
and spend very little time talking about the most
interesting portion of of of the paper. I think
because the AI can't distinguish sort of what
is hard what is difficult because by brute force
everything takes the same amount of time for them.
A human who has sort of naturally had to struggle
at the most difficult step of a paper would
naturally spend a lot of time on that step. And
so you need to write out the paper in a proof in
a way that it reads well and it can be explained
to other people. And then other people have to get
excited by it. they they they they have to accept
it as oh this is really interesting that this this
will help me solve my own problems or it really
um clarifies why this phenomenon was true that
it has to be accepted and this is where we we
traditionally have the peer review process where
we we send papers to referees and if the referees
are are excited by this result then um the paper
gets accepted but you know there could be papers
that are technically they are correct and and
they are readable and fine but but they could
answering a question that no one cares about. And
then finally, it needs to be sort of completely
polished and put into textbooks and and taught
to students. And often the first version of a
proof is not suitable for writing on textbooks.
It often is is done in a very inefficient way
and is not the the ordering of steps is not quite
logical. There's a certain digestion process where
where someone has to spend a lot of time thinking
very hard to what is completely the the right way
to organize to edit the paper to sort of flow in
the same way. a little bit like how you would you
would edit a documentary or a movie. And so what
we're finding is that AI tools are accelerating
the early stages of this process, but not the
late stages. We are now generating many proofs.
We are verifying a bunch of them, but the pace of
understanding them and putting them into the final
textbook form is still done by humans. Um, and in
fact, we're now experiencing what you might call
proof indigestion where suddenly there's lots
and lots of pending uh solutions to problems
that should be understood and should be go into
textbooks, but they just we're just flooded now
with with too many of them. Uh, and we have to
pick and we have to triage. And this is something
that has never had to happen before. Um it used
to be that solutions came out so rarely that um if
a solution to a major problem got got solved, all
the experts would sort of drop everything and read
it and and try to digest it as quickly as possible
because it was so rare and so valuable that it was
worth doing. And now we're just getting flooded
with with all these possible solutions. I myself,
you know, I've had to stop trying to stay current
with all the latest developments in in in in my
field. Sometimes there's just so much going
on. I I can't promise now to read every single
development that that that shows up. I mean, this
is already beginning to be a problem before AI,
but AI has really accelerated the sheer volume
of of content being generated. And so, we're
going to need much better curation and uh and
filtering. It's a good problem to have. I mean,
it's like it's better to have a to have too much
food, more food than you can eat than than not
enough food to eat. But it is still a problem.
AI have become increasingly capable in
mathematics. For people like me who have
been following the developments for the last
three years, um there's been a kind of steady
progression, you know, so four years ago they
could solve middle school math problems and then
they could solve high school math problems and
then uh high school Olympiad level problems and
then um some problems you like graduate student
um level qualifying exam problems and then
they're starting to solve a few of the the minor
um unsolved problems that maybe someone like
Paul Erdős would have proposed but no one really
looked at. So it's a lot of low hanging fruit.
And then just recently there's been one or two
occasions where they they managed to solve some
problems that people actually really did try very
hard to solve. Somehow collectively the humans
all had were taking the wrong turn and the AIs
which had a different set of biases had managed
to cobble together um a solution which was quite
clever and has been quite um has already had some
impact. there's been some nearby problems to uh
the unit distance problem for instance which have
also been solved by humans who have adapted the
uh the AI's technique. I found that quite
exciting. Uh so I think for some my colleagues
it was very concerning especially if they hadn't
been following the previous developments and and
and not realizing that this was where they were
at. If a colleague had only seen say what ChatGPT
could do in 2023 and if you asked it a difficult
math question then it would give you complete
rubbish and they they are quite different now.
And it's still fundamentally the same technology,
but but they have found ways to reduce the
error rate and and become genuinely useful. Now,
it's still unclear how replicable this is.
Many of these achievements um they're done
by private companies. They they not disclosing
how much resources they spent to to use. I mean,
is it was it $100,000 of commute compute? Was it
a million dollars? We don't really know. And we
don't know their success rate. um was this problem
that they solved the only problem that they looked
at or did they look at 10 problems? They look at
100 problems. While the results are impressive,
um we don't have enough data to to really gauge
whether this will become a completely regular
occurrence going forward or whether it's only if
you spend $100,000 over several months with a team
of 10 people that you can get results like this.
And maybe it's only 1% of all problems that we
care about are amenable to this method. uh yeah we
don't know but there are efforts to more properly
benchmark in a scientific way. The most recent
of these challenges is called the FrontierMath
challenge. They tested the latest models against
a test set of 10 research level questions and the
best models could do like five or six out of 10
of these sort of medium level difficulty math
problems which already had a solution but the
solution was kept secret that I think there's a
lot of routine tasks tasks that we we do every day
as a as a as in our research that some percentage
of those can now be done by by AIs. it could be
expensive. Uh many of of these tools they require
say a couple hundred dollars to run to before
they can get a solution and sometimes they fail.
They they spend all this compute and and they
end up with with nothing useful. We are seeing
now in programming that many expert programmers
are reporting that their ability to write code
has increased by a factor of five or 10 or 100
with these with these tools. But they are also
they can they can feel themselves learn losing the
ability to code by hand and sometimes they cannot
review the code that that that comes out of these
agents. There's a trade-off you know speed and is
not everything. I very much like the collaborative
aspect of mathematics. I didn't realize was so
important until relatively late in my career that
uh like a lot of the mathematics I've learned I I
learned after grad school by by working with uh
with mathematicians and and and scientists in
different fields. I teach them what I know, they
teach me what what what they know and I become
much broader as as as a as a as a result. When
you're working with a collaborator that you've
been working with a long time, um there's a point
where you become almost mentally attuned, perhaps
you've been familiar, like if it's a really close
friend or family member that you talk to for a
long time, sometimes you can complete each other's
sentences. You know what the other person's going
to say? And you can sometimes get that when you
collaborate. You can you can throw out an idea and
before you even finish the sentence, the other
person gets it and and can run with it. People
have tried to use AIs like this and AIs they are
you can't converse with them. Of course they make
mistakes sometimes they they sometimes will be
sycophantic and and only tell you what what you
want to hear but also the interactions right now
with these tools are kind of personal like I've
tried to collaborate with people um in person and
also have an AI present but breaks up the rhythm.
these these tools they don't they're not really
conversational like not as fluid conversation as
as as as they are with human collaborators yet.
uh maybe they will get they will get there until
recently they don't learn from your conversations
you know so with a collaborator when when you you
know you can resume the next day you can pick
up very quickly and sometimes even for a call
that you haven't met for years you can pick up
some very old threads AIs have a certain amount
of context and they can remember some things and
and they can record they can make notes and kind
of simulate this memory but you can't attune uh
to an AI the same way that you can to a really
close collaboration better yet. I actually don't
use these tools so much for the actual um problem
solving process. I found to date that these tools
are much better at secondary tasks like like doing
literature searches or or checking a proof or
writing some code, proofreading uh something
that I wrote to see if there's any opportunity
to make things a little bit tighter. I find,
yeah, the rhythm of of working with an AI is not
quite the the rhythm I I prefer working with a
human collaborator, but that could just be the
the current state of current technology. Maybe
future AIs will be much more conversational
and and much more human to interact with.
So we're at a somewhat risky point in in sort of
the uh the structure of of funding the scientific
enterprise in general because on the one hand
these tools are allowing us to create the outputs
of science or what seems to be the outputs of
science at at a much accelerated rate but it could
come at the cost of of nurturing our seed corn for
the next generation of scientists. For example,
there there is a real concern that um the training
problems that we give our graduate students to
work on to as as their as their first projects
to to get a little bit of of of recognition and
and and career training and experience. These
are the types of problems which now AIs can
um they can replicate many of the papers. But if
you replace the grad students by by these AIs,
you know, the AIs will generate these grad
student level papers, but then we won't get
the next generation of of of students. But if we
if we don't continue this process of digesting,
you know, all this AI output to build the next
base of knowledge for the next generation of
humans and AIs to to build upon that, we may end
up stagnating as as as a a scientific society. You
know, that we we'll be able to optimize everything
that we can we can do with our current technology,
but we may not actually develop really original
new ideas anymore. we will need to to really um
have a much more open discussion about what
basic science is and what is useful for and
why it's important to still have curiosity driven
research. why we still need a community of of of
of humans to explore things sometimes slowly,
sometimes you know in in in ways that are not
as efficient as the latest model AIs and also
the um the insights that that we that we we we
gain. I think um we should share them more and we
should do more outreach to to the general public.
I think the general public today, you know, they
can see the visible outputs of science. you know,
they have a cell phone, they have the internet,
they they they have GPS or whatever. Many people,
they they don't see the um the whole process
and and how a basic understanding of math and
science actually makes the world around them a
lot less scary and just a a lot a lot clearer.
I think a lot of people now are just living in in
a state of anxiety. The world is so complicated.
We haven't emphasized these s of softer values
of science as much as sort of the hard you know
like um technological outputs and things but
science does add a certain amount of clarity
to to to one's thinking and you know these are
valuable things and they need to be supported.